<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IMPRESSION-ESM</title>
    <description>Improving the physical process representation in Earth system models
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:10:58 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 10:10:58 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why icebergs and their interactions with sea ice should be included in Earth system models?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In June 2025, IMPRESSION-ESM funded an international 2-day workshop on icebergs, sea ice and the ocean in Paris. The workshop was organised by &lt;a href=&quot;https://pagesperso.locean-ipsl.upmc.fr/mvlod/&quot;&gt;Martin Vancoppenolle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://nicojourdain.github.io/&quot;&gt;Nicolas Jourdain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main conclusions of the workshop are summarized in a paper recently submitted to &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://hal.science/TRACCS-PC7-IMPRESSION-ESM/hal-05397165v1&quot;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-three researchers from France, Australia, Belgium, Canada, the UK, and Germany gathered in Paris for a two-day hybrid workshop (3–4 June 2025) to discuss iceberg–sea ice interactions and their representation in Earth system models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Icebergs and sea ice are two distinct forms of drifting ice, typically represented using different modelling approaches. Icebergs — relatively small in horizontal extent (500 m - 50 km long) but up to 700 m thick — calve from continental ice shelves and marine terminating glaciers and are modelled as Lagrangian particles. In contrast, sea ice, forming from the freezing of seawater, covers vast areas, spanning thousands of kilometers, but is much thinner (about 1 m thick), and modelled as a two-dimensional continuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current Earth system models generally assume that sea ice–iceberg interactions are negligible. However, mounting evidence indicates that processes essential to Antarctic sea ice and ocean dynamics — such as landfast sea ice and coastal polynyas — arise from dynamic iceberg–sea ice interactions.
Several Earth system modeling groups are actively addressing these interactions, resulting in a series of recent studies on icebergs, sea ice, and their interplay, which motivated the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations from 13 invited speakers, covering modelling and observational perspectives, formed the basis of discussions around the following themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iceberg, sea ice, and their interactions;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implications for the ocean;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perspectives on numerical and computational model infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/12/01/IcebergSeaIceWorkshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/12/01/IcebergSeaIceWorkshop/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Snow in Earth System Models Workshop, 17-21 November 2025, Aussois</title>
        <description>&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/SnowESMWorkshop2025.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A one-week workshop has been organized with 11 researchers from IPSL, Météo-France and IGE to set up a common framework for snow scheme developments. This workshop has clarified both the scientific requirements and the practical pathways for improving snow representation in Earth System Models (ESMs), with a particular focus on ORCHIDEE within IPSL-CM and SURFEX within CNRM-CM. Across applications ranging from mid-latitude seasonal snow to polar ice sheets, the group converged on a shared view: ESM-oriented snow schemes must prioritize physical consistency, numerical robustness, and computational efficiency, rather than exhaustive process-level details. At the same time, recent advances in observations and detailed snowpack modelling now make it possible to identify a limited but well-defined set of prerequisites that significantly enhance model realism and applicability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;core-developments-and-current-commitments&quot;&gt;Core developments and current commitments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these priorities, the ongoing development strategy within the group is centered on the use of a common snow scheme for glaciers, ice sheets and continental surfaces with four major axes including (i) improved snow optics through a spectral albedo scheme accounting for snow metamorphism and light-absorbing particles including a coupling with an aerosol scheme (postdoctoral work by Sujith Krishnakumar, LSCE/IGE), (ii) the inclusion of water isotopes in snow to enable process-based attribution studies (postdoctoral work by Sibin Simon, LSCE), (iii) improved representations of fresh snow properties, dry snow metamorphism, compaction and initialization over ice sheets (Philippe Conesa’s PhD, LSCE), and (iv) a more realistic treatment of liquid water percolation, refreezing, and ice layer formation (Glenn Pitiot’s PhD, IGE). Together, these developments will substantially improve the consistency of snow physics across surface types in IPSL- CM and place ORCHIDEE within the leading group of CMIP-class ESMs pursuing advanced, physically- based snow representations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluation-strategy-and-long-term-sustainability&quot;&gt;Evaluation strategy and long-term sustainability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key outcome of the workshop is the initiation of a coordinated effort to structure a unified evaluation strategy for snow, applicable across surface types and modelling configurations. The group has begun to organize around these questions, with participants, responsibilities, and scientific directions now clearly identified. The envisioned strategy will build on standardized 1D test cases over well-instrumented reference sites (seasonal snow in the French Alps and perennial snow at Dome C, Antarctic), complemented by distributed and coupled simulations at climate scales. Downstream evaluation and validation will further rely on sites from ESM-SnowMIP (Krinner et al., 2018) in North America (Reynolds Mountains) and Japan (Sapporo), as well as on RetMIP (Vandecrux et al., 2020) for Greenland percolation (Dye-2) and accumulation (Summit) zones. These sites, while documented at a more modest level of detail (e.g., lacking vertical profiles or spectral albedo measurements), provide valuable benchmarks for assessing model performance beyond the core test cases. It will progressively include the definition of common evaluation metrics, harmonized data formats, reference archives of observations and control simulations, and the systematic storage of model outputs to support continuous integration. This effort is being developed in close coordination with the ORCHIDEE group, with the objective of remaining aligned with existing practices and ensuring long-term sustainability, including the integration of developments into the main IPSL-CM trunk. To ensure the success and durability of the evaluation framework, the group identified a strong need for dedicated engineering support, for both model evaluation and continuous integration objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-issues-and-longer-term-perspectives&quot;&gt;Open issues and longer-term perspectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the workshop highlighted several important topics that remain largely unaddressed and will require dedicated efforts in the short to medium term : a surface energy balance with differentiated fluxes computed for subgrid tiles depending on surface type, conditions (snow amount in particular), elevation, slope and orientation (following Alleon 2024); the coupling between atmosphere and surface processes for blowing snow (e.g., Amory et al., 2021 ; Vignon et al., 2025); snow–vegetation interactions (e.g. Druel et al., 2019), depth hoar formation and vapor transport (e.g., Brondex et al., 2023); snow on sea ice (e.g., Brivoal et al., 2025), the possibility to simulate on-line the surface mass balance in a common way for ice sheets and glacier; and the closure of the global water budget in fully coupled configurations including the treatment of mass and energy exchanges across the ocean–atmosphere–ice triple interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further information can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sdrive.cnrs.fr/f/395267731&quot;&gt;workshop report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/11/17/Snow-Workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/11/17/Snow-Workshop/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Climate models, how to improve them?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For the September TRACCS monthly webinar, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnrm.meteo.fr/spip.php?article513&quot;&gt;Aurore Voldoire&lt;/a&gt; (CNRM) will discuss the following subjects: “Climate models, how to improve them?”
Let meet on Friday 19 September, 11h, under this &lt;a href=&quot;https://meteo.webex.com/meteo/j.php?MTID=m2ccb9d71ee3a9743a8d5539c08d31183&quot;&gt;webex link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/08/01/WebinaireTRACCS-Voldoire/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/08/01/WebinaireTRACCS-Voldoire/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD scholarship on convective clouds in climate models</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Applications are invited for an IMPRESSION-ESM-funded PhD position at CNRM, Météo-France &amp;amp; CNRS, Toulouse, France on the “representation of convective system clouds in climate models”.
Details on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umr-cnrm.fr/IMG/pdf/traccs-pc7_recrutement-these-wp1-enclumes_vf.pdf&quot;&gt;PhD project&lt;/a&gt; are provided on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umr-cnrm.fr/spip.php?article75&quot;&gt;CNRM website&lt;/a&gt; and application should be done &lt;a href=&quot;https://careers.flatchr.io/fr/company/meteofrance/vacancy/g8owlpglejjd63o1-doctorant-f-h&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/07/18/PhD-ConvectiveClouds/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/07/18/PhD-ConvectiveClouds/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Iceberg and sea-ice workshop, 3-4 June 2025, Paris</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Les 3 et 4 juin, trente-trois chercheur.e.s venu.e.s de France, d’Australie, de Belgique, du Canada, du Royaume-Uni et d’Allemagne se sont réunis à Paris pour un atelier hybride consacré aux interactions entre icebergs et glace de mer, ainsi qu’à leur représentation dans les modèles climatiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les icebergs et la glace de mer sont deux formes distinctes de glace dérivante dans l’océan, généralement représentées selon des approches de modélisation différentes. Les icebergs — de faible extension horizontale mais pouvant atteindre jusqu’à 500 m d’épaisseur — se détachent des plateformes de glace continentales et sont souvent modélisés comme des particules lagrangiennes. En revanche, la glace de mer, formée par le gel de l’eau de mer, couvre de vastes zones, est beaucoup plus mince (environ 1 m d’épaisseur) et est généralement représentée comme un continuum bidimensionnel dans les modèles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les modèles climatiques actuels considèrent en général que les interactions directes entre glace de mer et icebergs sont négligeables — une hypothèse sans doute valable pour l’Arctique, mais qui ne tient pas pour l’Antarctique. Il existe désormais des preuves claires que des phénomènes essentiels à la dynamique de la glace de mer et de l’océan, comme la glace de mer côtière (landfast) et les polynies, sont fortement influencés par les interactions dynamiques entre icebergs et glace de mer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plusieurs groupes de modélisation du système Terre à travers le monde, incluant les participant.e.s français.e.s à TRACCS s’emploient à intégrer des composants dynamiques des calottes glaciaires dans leurs modèles et à mieux représenter les interactions entre la glace d’origine continentale et les autres compartiments du système Terre. Cette dynamique a conduit à une série d’études récentes sur les icebergs, la glace de mer et leurs interactions, et a motivé l’organisation de cet atelier dans le cadre du projet ciblé TRACCS 7 IMPRESSION-ESM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les présentations de 13 intervenant.e.s invité.e.s — couvrant à la fois les aspects de modélisation et d’observation — ont servi de base aux discussions autour des thématiques suivantes :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Icebergs, glace de mer, et leurs interactions ;
Conséquences pour la dynamique océanique ;
Perspectives sur l’infrastructure numérique et computationnelle des modèles.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Les discussions et les résultats de cet atelier seront diffusés ultérieurement via la liste de diffusion IMPRESSION-ESM et sur le site du projet.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/04/Iceberg-Workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/06/04/Iceberg-Workshop/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome to Arthur Jardot, Grégoire Pain and Sujith Krishnakumar!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Arthur Jardot has just started an intern position at CNRM to evaluate the capacity of a range of models (ARPEGE-Climat, LMDZ and km-scale Meso-NH) to represent the shallow-to-deep convection transition in four contrasted environnement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;« J’ai entamé un stage de césure sur la représentation de la transition entre convection peu profonde et profonde, notamment dans les modèles de climats et kilométriques. Étudiant en école d’ingénieur à l’ISAE-SUPAERO, je cherche à allier les connaissances acquises dans mon cursus avec mon éthique environnementale. »&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grégoire Pain has joint the CNRM as a master intern to study boundary-layer processes along a forest-maize field edge, using both large-eddy simulations and observation from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mosai.aeris-data.fr/&quot;&gt;MOSAI&lt;/a&gt; P2OA field campain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=OGX3dmMAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Sujith Krishnakumar&lt;/a&gt; has just started a postdoctoral position at LSCE to work on the snow albedo parameterization in the IPSL climate model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;« I am currently working on physics based impure snow albedo development in ORCHIDEE of IPSL-CM model over the continental and glacier surfaces. I am always enthusiast about the model development of land surface process and coupled interaction with other components of earth system. »&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to all of them!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/04/01/New-Contributors/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/04/01/New-Contributors/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The 2025 General Assembly</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The hybrid 2025 General Assembly gathered more than 30 people on 6-7 February! More information under the &lt;a href=&quot;/GAs&quot;&gt;GAs webpage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/img/GA2025.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/07/GA2025/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/02/07/GA2025/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The IMPRESSION-ESM website is now online</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We are glad to launch this new website !!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2025/02/03/new-site/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2025/02/03/new-site/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
